Henry T. Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry T. Allen Papers 1806-1933 (bulk 1883-1933)
MSS10504
Allen, Henry T. (Henry Tureman), 1859-1930
15,000 items 62 containers plus 11 oversize 22 linear feet 3 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer. Correspondence, diaries, writings, reports, military documents, photographs, printed matter, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous material relating mainly to Allen's military career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen family.; Allen, Henry T. (Henry Tureman), 1859-1930.; Allen, Henry T. (Henry Tureman), 1859-1930. My Rhineland journal. 1923.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Bliss, Tasker Howard, 1853-1930--Correspondence.; Dresel, Ellis Loring, 1865-1925--Correspondence.; Harbord, James G. (James Guthrie), 1866-1947--Correspondence.; Herrick, Myron T. (Myron Timothy), 1854-1929--Correspondence.; Hyde, James H. (James Hazen), 1876-1959--Correspondence.; MacArthur, Arthur, 1845-1912--Correspondence.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964--Correspondence.; March, Peyton Conway, 1864-1955--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.; Tirard, Paul, 1879-1945--Correspondence.; Wallace, Hugh G.--Correspondence.; Weeks, John W. (John Wingate), 1860-1926--Correspondence.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927--Correspondence.
Organizations
Philippine Constabulary.; United States. Army --History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916.; United States. Army. Infantry Division, 90th.
Subjects
Elections--United States--1928.; Police--Philippines.; Veterans--United States--Societies, etc.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
Alaska--Discovery and exploration.; Germany--History--Allied occupation, 1918-1930.; Rhine River Valley--History.
Occupations
Army officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Henry T. Allen were given to the Library of Congress by his son, Henry T. Allen, Jr., in 1956.
Additional Guides
A note about the Henry T. Allen Papers appeared in the Library's Information Bulletin, vol. 16, no. 2 (14 Jan. 1957), and the material was described in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, vol. 14, no. 3 (May 1957), p. 118. In 1958, the Library published Henry T. Allen, a Register of His Papers in the Library of Congress.
Transfers
A portfolio of sketches of Aristide Briand has been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where it is identified as part of the Henry T. Allen Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry T. Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on three reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1859, Apr. 13 Born, Sharpsburg, Ky.
1882 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1887 Married Dora Johnston
1885-1886 Engaged in exploration of Alaska
1888-1890 Instructor, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1890-1895 Military attaché, Russia
1897-1898 Military attaché, Germany In Santiago Campaign as major and adjutant general In Philippines as lieutenant colonel, Forty-Third Regiment
1901 Governor, Island of Leyte Started organization of Philippine Constabulary; was its chief
1903 Brigadier general and chief of constabulary by act of Congress
1910-1912 Lieutenant colonel, General Staff, in charge of Cavalry Section, War Department
1916-1917 In Mexican Punitive Expedition as lieutenant colonel and colonel
1917 Organized cavalry brigade from Thirteenth Cavalry Regiment, Fort Riley, Kans. Assigned as commander, Ninetieth Division, Camp Travis, Tex.
1917-1918 Commanded Ninetieth Division at Toul, Saint-Mihiel, Meuse-Argonne, France
1918-1919 Commanded Eighth Army Corps at Montigny-sur-Aube, France
1919 Commanded Ninth Army Corps at Nogent-en-Bassigny, France Commanded Seventh Army Corps at Wittlich, Germany
1919-1923 Commanded American forces in Germany
1923 Retired from United States Army
1928 Active in organizing veterans' groups for Alfred Emanuel Smith for president; unsuccessful aspirant for Democratic vice-presidential nomination
1930, Aug. 30 Died, Burne Vista Spring, Pa.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Tureman Allen (1859-1930) span the years 1806-1933, with the bulk of the material dating from 1883 to 1933. The collection relates mainly to Allen's military career as a member of an Alaskan exploring party, 1885-1886; as organizer and chief of the Philippine Constabulary, 1901-1907; as a member of the Mexican Punitive Expedition, 1916-1917; as commander of the Ninetieth Division during the First World War, and as commander of the American Occupation Forces on the Rhine, 1919-1923. Subsequent to his retirement from the army in 1923, he was active in organizing various veterans' groups for the 1928 Democratic presidential candidate, Alfred Emanuel Smith; material relating to this political activity is among the papers. A few Allen family papers are also in the collection. The papers are organized into the following series: Diaries, General Correspondence, Letterbooks, Military Matters, Speech, Article, and Book File, Miscellany, Photographs, Printed Matter, Clippings, Maps, Reports, Photograph Albums, Scrapbooks and Portfolio, and Oversize.
The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, personal as well as professional. Included, too, are diaries, manuscripts of a book, My Rhineland Journal, and numerous speeches and articles, reports of Allen's military activities, photographs, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in fourteen series:
Diaries, 1883-1930
General Correspondence, 1806-1933
Letterbooks, 1887-1924
Military Matters, 1900-1923
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1899-1930
Miscellany, 1847-1930
Photographs, circa 1890-1930
Printed Matter, circa 1890-1933
Clippings, 1901-1930
Maps, circa 1911-1923
Reports, 1918-1928
Photograph Albums, 1899-1923
Scrapbooks and Portfolio, 1884-1931
Oversize, 1884-1931
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78010504
Container List
- Diaries, 1883-1930 (Box 1-4)
  Diaries of Allen and his wife, Dora J. Allen.
  Arranged chronologically, with Dora Allen's diaries filed at the end of Container 1.
  - 1883-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1893-1895 (Box 1)
  - 1897-1898 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1906 (Box 1)
  - Dora J. Allen's diaries, 1894-1901 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 2)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 2)
  - 1917-1920, Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1920, Mar.-1922, June (Box 3)
  - 1922, July-1924, June (Box 4)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 4)
  - 1930 (Box 4)
- General Correspondence, 1806-1933 (Box 5-26)
  Letters sent and received including occasional family papers.
  Arranged chronologically.
  Partially available on negative microfilm. Shelf no. 19,102.
  - 1806-1895 (Box 5)
  - 1896-1899 (Box 6)
  - 1900-1902 (Box 7)
  - 1903-1905 (Box 8)
  - 1906-1910 (Box 9)
  - 1911-1916 (Box 10)
  - 1917-1919 (Box 11)
    Available on negative microfilm. Shelf no. 19,102, reel 1
  - 1920 (Box 12)
    - Jan.-May (Box 12)
    - June-July (Box 13)
    - Aug.-Oct. (Box 14)
    - Nov.-Dec. (Box 15)
  - 1921 (Box 16)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 16)
    - Apr.-July (Box 17)
    - Aug.-Dec. (Box 18)
  - circa 1921-1922, Apr. (Box 19)
  - 1922, May-Dec., circa 1922 (Box 20)
  - 1923 (Box 21)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 21)
    - Apr.-Dec. (Box 22)
  - 1924 (Box 22)
  - 1925-1926 (Box 23)
  - 1927-1928, Sept. (Box 24)
  - 1928, Oct.-1929 (Box 25)
  - 1930-1933, undated, fragments, and duplicates (Box 26)
- Letterbooks, 1887-1924 (Box 27-31)
  Letters received and sent.
  Arranged as letters received and letters sent and therein chronologically.
  - Letters received (Box 27)
    - 1887-1895 (Box 27)
    - 1919, June 23-1923, Feb. (Box 28)
    - 1923-1924, American Committee for the Relief of German Children (Box 29)
  - Letters sent (Box 30)
    - 1899-1900 (Box 30)
    - 1919, Jan.-1923, Feb. (Box 31)
- Military Matters, 1900-1923 (Box 32-35)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, transcripts, general, operations, and field orders, maps and sketches, ordinances, notes, minutes of meetings, speeches and writings, printed matter, and miscellaneous military papers.
  Arranged by military action.
  - Philippines (Box 32)
  - Mexican Punitive Expedition (Box 32)
  - First World War (Box 33-34)
    Available on negative microfilm. Shelf no. 19,102, Reels 2-3
  - Occupation of Germany (Box 35)
- Speech, Article, and Book File, 1899-1930 (Box 36-41)
  Handwritten and typewritten drafts and printed copies of speeches and articles as well as typescripts of Allen's book My Rhineland Journal.
  Arranged by type of material and thereunder chronologically.
  - My Rhineland Journal (Box 36)
    - Typescript (Box 36)
      - 1914-1919 (Box 36)
      - 1920-1921 (Box 37)
      - 1922-1923 (Box 38)
    - Final draft (Box 38)
    - Printer's copy (Box 39)
  - Other writings (Box 40)
    - 1899-1930 (Box 40)
    - Undated (Box 41)
- Miscellany, 1847-1930 (Box 42-43)
  Genealogical and biographical material, financial papers, and military honors.
  Chronological span dates provided, but otherwise unarranged.
  - 1847-1930 (Box 42)
  - 1878-1929 (Box 43)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1930 (Box 44-45)
  Photographs of Allen and various persons and scenes in his life.
  - circa 1890-1930 (Box 44)
  - circa 1890-1930 (Box 45)
- Printed Matter, circa 1890-1933 (Box 46-47)
  - 1890-1929 (Box 46)
  - 1919-1933 (Box 47)
- Clippings, 1901-1930 (Box 48-49)
  - 1912-1930 (Box 48)
  - 1901-1930 (Box 49)
- Maps, circa 1911-1923 (Box 50)
  Maps used for military campaigns and maneuvers.
  - circa 1911-1923 (Box 50)
- Reports, 1918-1928 (Box 51-62)
  Reports chiefly on the occupation of Germany after World War I.
  Arranged by title.
  - "Notes on Rhineland Commission and IARHC," 1920, Jan.-July (Box 51)
  - "State Department Reports IARHC" (Box 51)
    - Book A, 1920, Aug.-Dec. (Box 51)
    - Book B, 1921, Jan.-June (Box 51)
    - Book C, 1921, July-Dec. (Box 52)
    - Book D, 1922, Jan.-Mar. (Box 52)
    - Book E, 1922, Mar.-Dec. (Box 52)
    - Book F, 1923, Jan.-Feb. (Box 53)
    - Index to Books A-D (Box 53)
  - "American Military Government of Occupied Germany, 1918-1920" (Box 54)
    - Vol. 1 (Box 54)
    - Vol. 2 (Box 55)
    - Vol. 3 (Box 56)
    - Vol. 4 (Box 57)
  - "American Representation in Occupied Germany, 1920-1921" (Box 58)
    - Vol. 1 (Box 58)
    - Vol. 2 (Box 59)
  - "American Representation in Occupied Germany, 1922-1923" (Box 60)
  - "Ordinances IARHC 1 Jan.-Feb. 1922, Annex to History of American Representation in Occupied Germany 1922-1923" (Box 61)
  - "Democratic National Committee, 1928" (Box 62)
- Photograph Albums, 1899-1923 (Box 62)
  Photographs relating to occupied Germany, Marechal Joffre, and the Philippines.
  Arranged by subject.
  - See Oversize (Box 62)
- Scrapbooks and Portfolio, 1884-1931 (Box 62)
  Correspondence, photographs, clippings, and miscellany. Also includes portfolio of maps, photographs, and drawings at end of file.
  Chronologically arranged.
  - See Oversize (Box 62)
- Oversize, 1884-1931 (Box OV 1-OV 11)
  Photograph album, scrapbooks, and portfolio.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Photograph Albums (Box OV 1)
    - Occupied Germany (Box OV 1)
      - Vol. 1 (Container 62) (Box OV 1)
      - Vol. 2 (Container 62) (Box OV 2)
      - Vol. 3 (Container 62) (Box OV 3)
    - "Le Maréchal Joffre sur le Rhin" (Container 62) (Box OV 4)
    - Philippines, 1899-1916 (Container 62) (Box OV 5)
  - Scrapbooks and Portfolio (Box OV 6)
    - 1884-1916 (Container 62) (Box OV 6)
    - 1917-1918 (Container 62) (Box OV 7)
    - 1918 (Container 62) (Box OV 8)
    - 1928 (Container 62) (Box OV 9)
    - 1930-1931(Container 62) (Box OV 10)
    - Portfolio of maps, photographs, and drawings (Container 62) (Box OV 11)